All right, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ח, Peh Chet, 88. And we
pick up in the middle of פ"ז עמוד ב'. Peh Zayin Amud
Bet. We are dealing with the types of cases where a woman
makes an שבועה shvua to collect her כתובה. ketubah. She's required to.
The first is that she concedes that part of it has been
paid. That is not the classic מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat of the
תורה Torah because she is the one that is collecting, not the
one that is being collected from. So it is a דרבנן שבועה
D'Rabanan Shvua because we're concerned that maybe she forgot and the שבועה
shvua will require her to rethink it and to be doubly sure
once there's a concession that part of it has been paid, we
want to just, we're going to require that שבועה. shvua. And now
we move on to the next case, which is about 10 lines
from the bottom: עד אחד מעידה שהיא פרועה. Ed Echad Me'ida She-hi
Parua. Case number two: she comes to collect her כתובה, ketubah, the
husband says, 'I paid,' she says, 'You didn't.' Of course, we believe
her; she's got a כתובה, ketubah, he doesn't have a receipt. But
he has one witness who says it's been paid. And she has
to take her שבועה shvua to contradict the one witness. So here
we have a similar type of a back and forth. This also
sounds like a שבועה דאורייתא. Shvua D'Oraita. סבר רמי בר חמא למימר
שבועה דאורייתא. Savar Rami Bar Chama L'meimar Shvua D'Oraita. Rami Bar Chama
thought that we were talking about a biblical שבועה, shvua, דכתיב d'chtiv
because a verse says, לא יקום עד אחד באיש לכל עון ולכל
חטאת. lo yakum ed echad b'ish l'chol avon u'l'chol chatat. One witness
cannot rise up against a person for any sin or for any
transgression. לכל עון ולכל חטאת הוא דאינו קם. L'chol avon u'l'chol chatat
hu d'eino kam. He cannot be believed around any issue of like
any sin or transgression.
אבל קם הוא לשבועה. Aval kam hu l'shvua. He can rise up
against him to demand a שבועה. shvua. That is the basis of
the idea that an עד אחד, ed echad, in order to contradict
the testimony of an עד אחד—an ed echad עד אחד ed echad
doesn't actually win in court; it's not testimony that will win the
case—but it demands the other side make a שבועה shvua to contradict
it.
That has legal force. Exactly. Exactly.
And that's a סברא svara based on this interpretation of the פסוק.
pasuk.
Right. ואמר מר, V'amar Mar, and we teach, כל מקום ששניים מחייבין
אותו ממון, אחד מחייבו שבועה.
kol makom she-shnayim m'chayvin oto mamon, echad
m'chaivo shvua. Anytime—now, it doesn't mean if, like, an עד אחד ed
echad testifies that somebody ate חלב, chelev, you require a שבועה. shvua.
Interestingly, although here the דרשה drasha is about עון, avon, but normally
we say that an עד אחד ed echad by איסורים issurim is
absolutely worthless. So interestingly, although it's not in the context of the
פסוק, pasuk, we say that the emphasis of the עד אחד ed
echad is in monetary matters. So here and that's the only place
an עד אחד ed echad matters. So any place where two people
would obligate a person to pay out money, אחד מחייבו שבועה. echad
m'chaivo shvua. One עד ed requires a שבועה, shvua, not paying money,
but a שבועה shvua to contradict. So here one עד ed says
it's paid up. She needs a שבועה shvua to contradict the עד
אחד. ed echad. That seems reasonable. But אמר רבא, amar Rava, comes
Rava and says exactly like he said before about the sort of
conceding part of it has been paid. שתי תשובות בדבר. Shtei teshuvot
b'davar. There are two responses to this, two reasons why you're wrong.
חדא, Chada, number one, דכל הנשבעין שבתורה נשבעין ולא משלמין. d'kol hanishba'in
she-ba-Torah nishba'in v'lo m'shalmin. All cases where a person takes an oath
of the תורה, Torah, they take an oath and get out of
paying. Okay, והיא, v'hi, normally it's like, I say you owe me
a hundred dollars, you say you don't, I have a witness that
says you do. In order to get out of paying the hundred
dollars because I've got a witness to back me up, you take
an oath, and your oath allows you to not pay. והיא, V'hi,
in this case, נשבעת ונוטלת. nishba'at v'notlet. She swears, she takes the
oath, and she collects. Okay, your עד ed says you've paid up.
All right, but I've got a שטר. shtar. That שטר shtar is
two testimonies. That שטר shtar basically is testimony and your עד ed
should mean nothing. Right? And I should just be able to collect.
So by the way, I want to repeat what I said yesterday,
that when you contradict the idea of contradicting the עד אחד ed
echad lets things sort of stay the way, similar to the מודה
במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, stay the way they would have been. I say
you owe me money, you say, 'No, I don't.' Okay, so I
don't have any שטר, shtar, I don't have any evidence. You're basically
believed when you say, 'No, I don't.' I've got an עד אחד,
ed echad, that creates a problem, that creates a question. You neutralize
the עד ed and we go back to the status quo, which
is you don't pay me money.
Neutralize it with an oath.
Right. I take a, I have a שטר shtar that says you
owe me two hundred dollars. You say you don't. Okay, and an
עד ed says that you've paid it. Now, if it was without
the עד, ed, you would have had to pay me two hundred
dollars because I've got a שטר. shtar. An עד ed says you
pay it, that doesn't really have weight against the שטר, shtar, but
if we go ahead and we take a שבועה shvua and we
neutralize the עד, ed, then we go back to where we were
before, which is the שטר shtar lets me collect. So the structure
is the same. But Rava is saying even though the structure is
the same, biblically, the only person who takes the שבועה shvua is
somebody who is being demanded to pay money and the שבועה shvua
would get them out of is neutralizing the עד אחד ed echad
or the מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat and saying therefore they don't have
to pay. In this case, there's no biblical שבועה. shvua. Structurally it's
the same, but biblically, if I'm coming to collect and you have
an עד אחד, ed echad, that means nothing if I've got a
שטר shtar and therefore biblically I should collect. That is not the
case of the biblical שבועה. shvua. The biblical
שבועה— shvua So that's answer number one why it's not biblical, although
structurally it's similar. Number two is ועוד אין נשבעין על כפירת שיעבוד
קרקעות ve'od ein nishba'in al k'firas shibud karka'os
that there's here it's about a debt, a debt that has liens,
and if it's a debt with a שטר shtar that has liens
and there's an oath, the oath is about whether the liens exist
or not. So that's an oath relating to קרקע. karka. We don't
take an oath relating to the denial to anything relating to liens
on קרקע. karka. So there's two reasons why, although it's obviously conceptually
similar to the biblical oath, it's not actually the biblical oath. אלא
אמר רבא מדרבנן, ella amar Rava mi-drabbanan, so it's only rabbinic, כדי
להפיס דעתו של בעל, kedei le-hafis da'ato shel ba'al, in order to
just, you know, appease the husband. The husband says, I've got an
עד אחד, ed echad, now how much is it going to appease
him? He actually says he really did pay. He's not saying maybe
I paid, and to sort and to quash, you know, sort of
to calm his any, you know, any misgivings, we're having him make
an oath, you know, that would be להפיס דעתו. le-hafis da'ato. Here
he actually says, I know I paid and I have a witness
to back me up. So it's not exactly clear how her making
an oath is going to calm him. If anything it's just going
to anger him more. You know, he now she made a false
oath too and now you're going to believe her? So I don't
know exactly what the answer to that is, but the reason here
that the גמרא Gemara doesn't say the more obvious thing, why does
it make it about the husband's sort of, you know, displeasure or
the husband's, you know, his being like upset and to and to
calm him down, why doesn't it just say, since there's an עד
אחד ed echad that leads that creates some objective concern that maybe
he actually did pay? And since there's some objective concern that he
actually did pay, we do this in order to for us as
the בית דין beis din to feel more assured, you know, that
that's not really the case, you know, to really address the possibility
that she's lying, that she did pay. And the reason I think
is, and this goes back to what I said yesterday, is that
there's always this question around a שבועה, shvuah, which is, if somebody
is willing to steal, then how is the שבועה shvuah going to
help? Now maybe we say, yeah, people will steal but they won't
make false oaths. But maybe not. That's the question in the גמרא
Gemara in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia whether חשוד אממון חשוד אשבועתא. chashud
al mammon chashud al shvuasah. And if we say that people who
will steal will make false oaths, then we have to explain every
single case of an oath as that the person has not until
this point been intentionally stealing, right? That they've somehow rationalized it or
some other type of a thing that the oath is going to
make them own up. So yesterday when the issue was that it
was a case where part has been paid, we say, well, maybe
she's making an honest mistake, right? Maybe the maybe the fact that
some has been paid means all's been paid and that she actually
wasn't paying so close attention and the oath will make her sort
of, you know, review the account. Okay, but here it's not that
it's partially been paid. Here it's like he says I paid it
all and she says you paid nothing. So it's not reasonable to
say she she completely forgot the full payment. But it might be
reasonable to say she remembered part of it and not all. Anyway,
so it doesn't have that option. And so the so what it
should have said is, okay, maybe she's lying and the oath will
make her admit. But again it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara doesn't
want to go there. It wants to speak about the function of
an oath assuming that because assuming that if somebody is lying, maybe
an oath won't do any good. So we have to make some
other assumption to explain what function the oath is doing. So if
she's willfully lying, we don't think it—the implicit in this גמרא Gemara
is it's very doubtful the oath will do any good. So what's
the point of the oath? The point of the oath is that
this עד אחד ed echad has the husband all riled up, so
she'll make an oath so that'll at least make him feel better.
At least he got an oath out of her. Again, I'm not
exactly sure how it makes him feel better. He'll feel that she's
just backing up her lie with an oath, but anyway, that is
why the גמרא Gemara I think does not say the most obvious
thing, which is, why did we make this oath? Because you got
an עד אחד ed echad that raises certain questions. Have her make
an oath. No, that gets then to the issue that if she's
lying about one thing, if she's stealing, she'll make a false oath,
so we have to make it about something else.
Yeah, so first of all two things. One is that what this
point that you're raising speaks to the relational dimension of this whole
thing. In other words, the husband could very well feel that if
my wife—she I don't really believe she's like a liar and and
untrustworthy. She's really willing to make the oath, so then I guess
that's really what it is and I was wrong, or something like
that.
Could be. Although it's pretty funny. He's saying, I definitely paid you
and I've got an עד. ed.
And he's forcing her, he's forcing her, and he probably doesn't like
her so much anyway. Well, I don't know. All right. So so
so the other question is, the biblical oath, the biblical oath is
usually for the person so that they do not have to pay,
right? So why don't we say though in that case המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah and have the the force legally
be on the other person who's tried to extract the money?
We do. But with an and the עד אחד ed echad or
those circumstances are—that's why once the oath is made, you're back to
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
Ah, it's because of the עד אחד ed echad again in that
instance.
Exactly, that's what I'm saying. Right. The basic dynamic is you're פטור,
pattur, but now we've got this thing that has to be neutralized
by the
שבועה. shvuah.
What do you mean only with a biblical oath? When there is
an עד אחד Ed Echad it is a biblical oath.
That is not a biblical oath, right?
Because the person who is collecting is making the oath.
Right. So but are we still applying the concept of if there's
one witness in this case it will still force her to make
the oath?
Yes, she does make an oath. There is one witness. No, no,
no, that's the משנה. Mishna. There's one witness she makes an oath.
We'll only try to explain what the nature of the oath is.
And he says it's a rabbinic one. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, אי פיקח
הוא, I pike'ach hu, if the husband is smart, מטי לה לידי
שבועה דאורייתא. mati lah liydei shvuah d'oraita. He can get her to
make a biblical oath. Now, before we get how he can turn
this into a biblical oath, what difference does it make? An oath
is an oath. So רש"י Rashi says, I mean which gets to
the question of
why the גמרא Gemara is so questioning like what type of an
oath is this? But that could be an abstract question. Oh, is
this a דאורייתא d'oraita case? No, no, no, it's דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Fine.
But here if you're trying to get her to make a דאורייתא
d'oraita oath, it sounds like there's a practical difference. So what's that
practical difference? So let's look at רש"י, Rashi, לידי שבועה דאורייתא, liydei
shvuah d'oraita,
שהיא בשם, she-hi be-shem, which is with God's name,
או בכינוי, o be-chinuy, or with some other God's name, בכינוי be-chinuy
is
not the Yud-Kay-Vav-Kay, but some other אלוקים, Elokim, שדי, Shaddai, something like
that, ואוחז ספר
תורה בידו, ve-ochez sefer Torah be-yado, and you hold a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, כדאמרינן בשבועות. ki-d'amrinan bi-shvuos. וחמורה היא מאד, Ve-chamura hi me'od,
it's very weighty, presumably both psychologically and maybe metaphysically. אבל שבועה דרבנן,
Aval shvuah d'rabbanan, but if it's only a rabbinic oath,
קללה בעלמא, klala be-alma, it's just a curse. It's just like saying,
"Oh, if I'm lying, let me be let a million curses befall
my head," or something like that.
Does it sound like it's a less serious thing?
Well, they'll take the anyway, they'll say,
"In God's name," but anyway, it's
feeling so okay, got it. Also there's all this whole description of
how they would impose the oath. It'll be a dark room with
lit candles, they blow שופרות. shofaros. Anyway, so psychologically it would be
very, very weighty and also if part of the whole weight of
a שבועה shvuah is לא ינקה השם את אשר ישא שמו לשוא,
lo yenakeh Hashem es asher yisa shemo la-shav, so it's using God's
name falsely, and then if it's not with God's name, it's
obviously is much less weighty both psychologically and metaphysically. So that's what
רש"י Rashi says, so we want it to be a שבועה דאורייתא,
shvuah d'oraita, the husband, in order that maybe it will really get
her to own up in ways that a שבועה דרבנן shvuah d'rabbanan
would not. תוספות Tosafot disagrees. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, מטי
לה לידי שבועה דאורייתא, mati lah liydei shvuah d'oraita, פירש בקונטרס, peireish
be-kuntres, דנפקא
מינה d'nafka mina between שבועה דאורייתא shvuah d'oraita and שבועה דרבנן, shvuah
d'rabbanan, דבדאורייתא מנח חפצא, d'bi-d'oraita manach heftza, מנח ספר תורה, manach Sefer
Torah, ובדרבנן לא נקיט. u-ve-d'rabbanan lo nakit. And not rabbinic. והוא עצמו
סותר דבריו, Ve-hu atzmo soter devarav, and then he says no, actually,
another רש"י Rashi shows it's not true, that even by a דרבנן
d'rabbanan we do it with holding onto a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
and the whole thing. And then תוספות Tosafot makes it more some
technical differences
about whether you can reverse the שבועה shvuah on the other person
or whatever. It's not as immediately obvious according to תוספות Tosafot why
it's so important to make it into a שבועה דאורייתא. shvuah d'oraita.
But okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. אי פיקח הוא
מטי לה לידי שבועה דאורייתא. I pike'ach hu mati lah liydei shvuah
d'oraita. He can make her make a biblical oath. How? She's not
the one, she's the one collecting, not the one paying, so it
can't be a שבועה דאורייתא, shvuah d'oraita, and there's the קרקע karka
issue. So here's what you do: יהיב לה כתובתה באפי חד סהדא.
Yahiv lah kesuvtasa be-apei chad sahada. Go ahead, pay out the כתובה,
ksuvah, because you're going to have to do it anyway if she
makes the oath. So go ahead and pay out the כתובה ksuvah
in front of another witness. A different witness. So
ראובן Reuven is the guy testifying that I paid the כתובה ksuvah
in
January and now so you're not believed or whatever and I'm going
to have to pay her out if she takes the oath anyway.
So okay, pay her again in May in front of a different
witness, in front of שמעון. Shimon.
So he's paying her twice?
Yeah, apparently he's paying her twice. But I'm going to have to
do that anyway once she takes the oath. Okay, so everybody got
that? Meaning I'm figuring out I'm going to lose that money anyway.
She's going to take the oath. I'm assuming she's going to take
the oath. So I'm going to lose the money anyway.
This scenario is assuming she's been lying all along.
Right, this is from the husband's perspective. From the husband's perspective that
she's been lying and you already paid it out. What can you
do to give yourself a more advantageous position? And what you can
do is, you're going to have to accept the fact that you're
going to have to pay out the money anyway, assuming that you
take it for granted she's going to make this oath. So here's
what you should do: pay it out now, in front of a
witness, in front of a different witness, שמעון. Shimon. וסמיך סהדותא דהאי
אסהדותא דהאי. Ve-samich sahadusa d'hai a-sahadusa d'hai. Get ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon to now get together. They both testify that I've paid the
כתובה, ksuvah, one in January and one in May, but they both
have seen that. ומוקי לה אהינא. Ve-moki lah a-haina. And therefore I'm
going to say to her, I paid your כתובה. ksuvah. She's obviously
not going to be able to deny it because I've got the
two witnesses, although from two different events, we're assuming somehow I can
combine them. We'll question that later. All right, I understand. The easiest
thing would just have had two witnesses during May, but let's just
bracket that for now. Bottom line is she can't deny that I've
paid her, that I paid her the May one. Okay, so I
paid her May. That's without question. Now I'm going to say, okay,
כתובה. ksuvah. כתובה, Ketubah, I paid you in May, I have witnesses,
great. Now by the way hon,
where's the hundred dollars I lent you in January? What do you
mean a hundred dollars you lent me in January? You never lent
me a hundred. Sure, call over ראובן. Reuven. ראובן, Reuven, didn't I
give her a hundred dollars in January? Now remember when I gave
her the hundred dollars in January, that was the כתובה Ketubah payment.
But now we've established that I paid off the כתובה Ketubah in
May. So if I paid off the כתובה Ketubah in May, what
was that hundred dollars in January? Right? So I'm saying it's a
loan. You say ah, you never oh look here's the witness. So
I say you owe me a hundred dollars, you deny it, I
have a witness, that's an עד אחד ed echad and now you're
you have to take an oath to get out of paying, which
is a שבועה דאורייתא. shvua d'oraisa. Okay, so once I've paid up
the כתובה Ketubah and I want to go back to the hundred
dollars I say I've already paid, now I'm trying to get money
out of the woman, and then she is the and then that's
the classic I'm not she's not the one who wants to be
paid, I'm the one who wants to get the money back, and
then that's the classic case of an עד אחד, ed echad, yes.
Why
do you give the why do you say give the second time
with one עד?
ed? Because that's been two. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
get to that. It's just making it complicated. It's true.
The real this assumes you haven't gone to בית דין Beis Din
already and said before that the first one was not a loan,
because if I did that, I'm in a כשאני אומר. k'she-ani omer.
Exactly, right. Well, you don't say that by the בית דין, Beis
Din, but yes. But anyway, okay, so let's take a look. So
מתקיף לה, matkif lah,
ומוקי לה להנך קמאי במלווה, u'moki lah l'hanach kama'ei b'milva, and then
basically claim that the earlier stuff is about a loan. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב ששת, matkif lah Rav Sheshes,
רב ששת Rav Sheshes says, בריה דרב אידי, breih d'Rav Idi, היכי
סמכת אסהדי קמאי אסהדי בתראי? heich samchat asahadi kama'ei asahadi basrai? How
do you combine the January witness with the May witness? Right? They're
different they're different events. Now of course in דיני ממונות dinei mamonus
sometimes you can combine witnesses of different events because bottom line they
both testify that I gave her the money. But it's also going
to be funny using the January witness at one moment to claim
that I paid the כתובה Ketubah and to prevent her from saying
I didn't, and then turn around and use the January witness to
say that I lent her a hundred dollars. Right? The January witness
can't claim the same hundred dollars was two things. So he says
that's weird. So let's make it easier. אלא אמר רב ששת בריה
דרב אידי, ela amar Rav Sheshes breih d'Rav Idi, יהיב לה כתובתה
באפי סהדי קמאי וסהדי בתראי. yeihiv lah kesuvata b'apei sa'adi kama'ei v'sa'adi
basrai. In May, call over
ראובן Reuven and say ראובן, Reuven, I need your help again. Okay,
my wife is denying the כתובה Ketubah I paid her in January.
Come here, I'm going to have to pay her again. And let's
get you together with שמעון Shimon and now I'm going to pay
her. So you could have just said I got two other guys,
שמעון Shimon and לוי. Levi. But alright, somehow we want to reuse
ראובן. Reuven. I'm going to be needing you again, believe me, because
we're going to do this a stage one and then there's a
stage two coming back. So ראובן, Reuven, you come here with שמעון,
Shimon, watch me pay her the two hundred dollars in May. And
then or whatever the two and then I'm going to go back
and ask her I keep on switching between two hundred and a
hundred. And then I'll go back and I'm going to talk about
what the two hundred dollars I gave her in January. Okay? So
go ahead and get two witnesses now on the during in May.
Okay. בריה דרב אידי יהיב לה כתובתה באפי סהדי קמאי וסהדי בתראי
ומוקי לה להנך קמאי בחובה. breih d'Rav Idi yeihiv lah kesuvata b'apei
sa'adi kama'ei v'sa'adi basrai u'moki lah l'hanach kama'ei b'hova. And then go
back, now I've got two witnesses I paid you in May the
full the two hundred dollars. Now I'm going to go back and
ask for the two hundred dollars I gave you in January and
I'm going to say it's a loan and you're going to deny
it and I'm going to have a witness
and you're going to have to make a שבועה דאורייתא shvua d'oraisa
on it. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב אשי, matkif
lah Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asks on this, אכתי יכלה
למימר בי כתובות הואי? akati yahla l'meimar bei kesuvos havai? I don't
get it. She says why are you going to be believed to
claim that January was a loan? Right? I mean she'll just say
what are you talking about? January you were paying off a כתובה.
Ketubah. So okay, I was paying off a כתובה. Ketubah. But how
could I say that? I have two witnesses I paid off a
כתובה Ketubah in May. She says you know what actually? You loved
me so much that you wrote two separate כתובות kesuvos for me.
Okay? And two and you let me collect two כתובות. kesuvos. Which
is an interesting phenomenon. So instead of rewriting the original כתובה Ketubah
for four hundred dollars, you wrote one כתובה Ketubah for two hundred
and another כתובה Ketubah for two hundred. So you paid up the
first כתובה Ketubah in January and the second כתובה Ketubah you paid
up in in May. So okay, so it's not a loan. I
don't owe you any money. I don't have to give it back.
Alright, so why are you going to be believed? You're going to
claim it's a loan and say she has to pay it back
and she's going to claim no you were paying off some debt.
And actually ראובן Reuven who knows that in January it was payment
for a כתובה Ketubah is going to essentially back her statement. If
we ask ראובן, Reuven, ראובן, Reuven, yes you saw him give two
hundred dollars, was there some discussion of what the context was? Yes,
it was a כתובה Ketubah context. Okay. So now she'll just say
great, you paid me up my January כתובה Ketubah in January, my
May כתובה Ketubah in May.
Which is wouldn't have to bring any documentation that there are two
כתובות? kesuvos? What?
Doesn't some have to be produced at some point that there are
two כתובות? kesuvos?
No, I you basically gave me a hundred dollars and a witness
and I say it was payment of a debt. Okay. And you've
got- And the witness backs me up, right?
And there's no שטר. shtar. Right?
There's no right? Meaning, what's the evidence? Basically, you're right now המוציא
מחבירו. hamotzi m'chaveiro. You say you you come without any evidence that
you say that you say that you lent me money. Okay, and
I say and I say you didn't lend me money. And now
okay, so your whole evidence that creates that changes the dynamic is
the עד אחד. ed echad. Okay, but if I question the עד
אחד ed echad and I say really? You're you're backing him up
when he says he lent me that money? Did he say at
that time that he was paying me up a debt? And the
עד אחד ed echad says yeah, he did actually
say he was paying up a debt. So the עד אחד ed
echad is no longer backing you up, right? Yeah, but what if
they put the כתובה ketubah on the table?
I don't have to show proof that there was a debt, so
maybe there are two כתובות. ketubot. Now, of course you could say
that that's very rare that there were two כתובות, ketubot, and we'll
get to that in a minute. But ignoring the rareness of two
כתובות, ketubot, okay, I don't have to prove it was a debt.
The only proof you have that is your עד אחד. ed echad.
And your עד אחד ed echad concedes that the context was the
payment of a debt, so I don't need to bring any other
proof. All right, so now let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
מתקיף לה רב אשי אכתי יכל למימר בי כתובות הוי אלא רב
אשי הוא דמודי להו. Matkif lah Rav Ashi, ata k'tei yachol lomeir
bei k'tuvot havai, ela Rav Ashi hu de'modeh lehu. So here's where
it basically gets to the point. What Michael goes ahead or let's
not say Michael, what I go ahead and do because I'm getting
it from my wife is, before I get ראובן Reuven to to
see what I'm that I'm going to pay her again in May,
I say ראובן, Reuven, look, here's the story. You and I both
know that I paid her in January. Okay, but I don't have
enough witnesses, she's denying that I paid her. I'm going to have
to do this whole thing in order to get into a שבועה
דאורייתא. shvu'ah d'oraisa. So I'm going to pay her now in order
to do this whole thing, but I want you to be aware
that this payment is really for the original repaying the original thing
I paid in January. This isn't some second כתובה, ketubah, I'm repaying
the original thing. So I've brought ראובן Reuven into my confidence about
what I'm up to. And therefore somehow that's going to mean that
when ראובן Reuven now comes and testifies that money was given in
January and she says oh yeah that was for there were two
כתובות, ketubot, ראובן Reuven is going to say no, I actually know
that there weren't two כתובות, ketubot, the husband basically told me he
was just having to repay for the first one. Now somehow it's
like okay, big deal, that's just the husband's claim and ראובן Reuven
is just, you know, is just echoing back the husband's version of
the event. But what רש"י Rashi says is that in that scenario
because two כתובות ketubot is so rare, right? When do we ever
have two כתובות? ketubot? Because it's so rare, and now ראובן Reuven
is basically saying as far as I know, I saw two payments,
but from my understanding of what that was about, it was the
same payment for the same thing, okay, and that he was just
forced to do that. So that's enough to make us very skeptical
of the claim that it was two כתובות ketubot and being willing
to say it looks like the husband gave you an extra an
extra two hundred dollars, you have to give that back and turn
it into a case of a classic עד אחד דאורייתא. ed echad
d'oraisa. Okay, so it's very complicated, but the upshot is pay up
now and then go back and ask for the money you already
paid, and that'll turn it into a שבועה דאורייתא. shvu'ah d'oraisa. Okay
the problem is of course that if the woman is what this
does is, is this means the most you will get out of
this, right? Will be like what's the best case scenario in here?
If she's
willing to take the שבועה, shvu'ah, right? What? You're not getting the
money anyway, right? If she's anyway now you might think she'll she'll
make a false שבועה דרבנן shvu'ah d'rabbanan but she won't make a
false שבועה דאורייתא. shvu'ah d'oraisa.
So this way is eventually forcing her into this spot will then
make her pay off that that two hundred dollars because now she'll
have to make a שבועה דאורייתא. shvu'ah d'oraisa. But you know, there's
the the you're taking a risk for the other possibility, which is
she wouldn't have
made the שבועה דרבנן, shvu'ah d'rabbanan, she wouldn't
she would not have taken a false oath, even the שבועה דרבנן,
shvu'ah d'rabbanan, she would have you you would have saved your whole
two hundred dollars, right? And now is it any worse? Now? Yes,
because now you have paid her
twice and you're not going to...
No, but either way either way you break even, right?
In scenario number one... You're right.
She unless she...
If she didn't take the שבועה shvu'ah then you've already paid. And
in this case, you paid her twice, she won't take the שבועה,
shvu'ah, you'll get the two hundred back, so you'll also yeah. So
okay, it makes sense. You you stand to gain through this process.
Doesn't this whole סוגיא sugya undermine the entire thrust of the סוגיות
sugyos we've been learning to try to protect the woman? And so
here's like, and here's how you can be duplicitous in...
No, not at all. I think this is not I you know,
the גמרא Gemara will often do this. It has it doesn't matter
if it's husband and wife or ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, and
it I the גמרא Gemara does this all the time, and it
could have been the exact reverse, that the woman's in a disadvantageous
position and the גמרא Gemara is saying here's how she could you
know, here's how she could make it better. So the גמרא Gemara
just sort of I don't think that this is about siding with
the husband, it's just גמרא Gemara pointing out from your perspective... you're
the one who's being like who's telling the truth and the other
side is lying here's how you can go about this in a
more advantageous way. Now why that's not כעורכי הדיינין k'orchei hadayanin which
is a סוגיא sugya that the גמרא Gemara has elsewhere, okay, but
the גמרא Gemara is also doing it because it's an interesting like
intellectual exercise like what's the way you know that
there's a legal structure
exactly that would enable you exactly to respond to this situation. Right.
That if right, exactly.
That if this were to be put in place and then you
could have this type of exactly situation.
Exactly. Okay and earlier גמרות Gemarot if you remember did things in
order saying about how a woman could make her situation better, you
know, within the legal structure.
You do it in front of two witnesses. Okay.
fine. exactly. Well that's always the lesson. מנכסים משועבדים menichasim meshubadim just
take out your iPhone snap a picture you're done. Okay.
Yes. why is the thing with קרקע karka why is there no
שבועה shvua with קרקע?
karka? Yeah,
I'm not no it's גזירת הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv I don't want to
get into any speculation about that right now. תנן התם. Tnan hatam.
Now,
the next case that a woman has to take a שבועה shvua
in collecting her כתובה kesubah is that the guy is dead. So
the first case was a claim that it's been paid or paid
and then some evidence that it's been paid. The next case is
he's not around to make any claim. He's excuse me we're not
he's not dead yet. He's not around because I'm not dead yet.
Okay. He's not around because he's because she's collecting from people that
purchased land off of her and she's exercising her lien. Okay. And
the people that have bought the land say well for all I
know he paid and he has a receipt and how do I
know that he hasn't already paid it off? Okay. So there's a
claim that not that the husband claims it's been paid but the
husband isn't claiming anything and you're trying to collect from some third
party and therefore she has to take an oath that it hasn't
been paid. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught over there in שבועות.
Shvuos. וכן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה V'chen hayetomim lo yifre'u ella
bishvuah
heirs can only collect from a
שבועה shvua with a שבועה. shvua. So if heirs are coming to
collect their father rent money and died and they have all of
these IOU all of these like שטרות shtarot לקוחות lekuchos all the
creditors' heirs. No, we're not doing לקוחות. lekuchos. Now we're actually dealing
with the with the יתומים yetomim case. Okay which is actually why
I was right the first time even though the phrase here is
נכסים משועבדים nechasim meshubadim there are two cases in the גמרא Gemara
where of where he's not around. Actually three but we'll do with
two now. One is I go to the לקוחות lekuchos and the
other is the guy died and the woman is coming to collect
from his heirs. שלא בפניו shelo befanav שלא בפניו shelo befanav is
the third one we'll get to him where he's in Hawaii. But
right now I'm either going
the word orphan only refers to the father being passed away? Yes.
In other words the mother's still alive.
You can't call it orphan. Yes. Correct. I mean I don't know
I mean in other cases maybe not but here certainly. Here it's
more orphans that are heirs. So it's about the father having died.
So okay. So right now we're dealing with two out of the
three cases, right? There are three cases where he's not around. One
is he's in Hawaii we will get to that. The other is
is that I'm going to the לקוחות lekuchos the people that have
the property and the third is which is really the second in
the משנה mishna which we're going to focus on is that he's
dead. Okay and I'm going and I'm collecting from the heirs. In
all those cases maybe he paid and he's not around to say
otherwise so I the woman have to take an oath. Okay so
we're now going to hone in on the case about he's collecting
from the heirs. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught over there in
שבועות. Shvuos. וכן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה V'chen hayetomim lo yifre'u
ella bishvuah heirs of the creditor have to make an oath when
they collect. Okay so let's take a look at this. Right presumably
the the heirs that the oath that the heirs would make is
is that we have no evidence that our father never told us
that these loans were paid off and we have no evidence in
any of his records that these loans have been paid off because
when I normally go ahead and I collect a loan itself I
am implicitly not only producing the שטר shtar but implicitly saying the
loan hasn't been paid or explicitly saying. But the heirs maybe they
don't know if the loan hasn't been paid or not so they
have to basically take an oath that to the best of their
knowledge it hasn't been paid.
So these are orphans of the debtors.
Right these are heirs of the creditor. וכן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא
בשבועה. V'chen hayetomim lo yifre'u ella bishvuah. ממאי? Mimai?
Who are they collecting from? אילימא מלווה? Ileima miloveh? If they're going
straight to the to the borrower השתא אביהן שקיל בלא שבועה אינהו
בשבועה? Hashta avihin shakil belo shvuah inhu bishvuah? The father can collect
without an oath. They have to make an oath? Now the answer
is well why not the father is claiming he knows that it
hasn't been paid but okay but the father doesn't have to make
an oath that it hasn't been paid so let them say without
an oath to the best of our knowledge it hasn't been paid.
Right why all of a sudden do they have to make an
oath they they have the document they have the שטר. shtar. Let
them say to the best of their knowledge it hasn't been paid
and let them collect. So אלא הכי קאמר. Ella hachi ka'amar. Here's
what it must mean. וכן יתומים מן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה.
V'chen yetomim min hayetomim lo yifre'u ella bishvuah. That if heirs are
coming to collect from heirs so the same way when the creditor
goes straight Goes to the heirs, he has to make a שבועה,
shvua, right? Because that's the case. The creditor's going to the heirs,
so the actual borrower isn't there to make a counterclaim, isn't there
to say, "Here's my receipt, I paid," or whatever. So when you're
collecting from heirs, you have to make a שבועה shvua because the
guy isn't around to defend himself. So you have to make a
שבועה shvua to back up your claim. So if the creditor is
dead and his heirs are collecting from the borrower's heirs, so they
also have to make a שבועה. shvua. Their claim is not it
hasn't been paid, their claim is to the best of our knowledge
it hasn't been paid. Okay, but you got it? If I'm collecting
straight from the לוה, loveh, let him defend himself and I just
say, and I don't have to make an oath, and my heirs
don't have to make an oath. I say it hasn't been paid,
my heirs say to the best of our knowledge, that's it. The
לוה loveh wants to say otherwise, let him argue otherwise. But if
the לוה loveh is dead and he can't argue otherwise, right, then
I have to take an oath that it hasn't been paid, and
if it's not me and it's my heirs, they have to take
an oath that to the best of their knowledge it hasn't been
paid. Okay? So that's the idea of collecting from יתומים. yetomim. All
right. אמר רב זריקא אמר רב יהודה. amar Rav Zerika amar Rav
Yehuda. לא שנו אלא שאמרו יתומים אמר לנו אבא לויתי
ופרעתי. lo shanu ela she'amru yetomim amar lanu aba lovisi ufarati. When
is it that you have to take an oath to collect from
the heirs? When they say our father told us that he borrowed
and paid. And then you say take an oath that he didn't
pay. Or you take an oath that if you're the heirs, that
to the best of your knowledge he didn't pay. אבל אמרו, aval
amru,
but if the heirs say, אמר לנו אבא, amar lanu aba, our
father told us, לא לויתי, lo lovisi, I never borrowed money. So
they deny the debt completely. אף בשבועה לא יפרעו, af bishvua lo
yifru, then you can't even collect even with an oath. Which is
crazy! I've got a שטר, shtar, right? I got a שטר! shtar!
So they're saying he never borrowed, so because they're denying it whole
hog, therefore I can't collect even though I got a שטר shtar
that says he did borrow? So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה
רב אשי. matkif lah Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav Ashi asks,
אדרבה, aderaba, the opposite makes sense. כל אומר לא לויתי כל אומר
לא פרעתי דמי. kol omer lo lovisi kol omer lo parati dami.
If you say you didn't borrow, you're implicitly saying you didn't pay,
and this guy's got a שטר shtar that you did borrow. אלא
אימא הכי איתמר, ela eima hachi itamar, if it was said here,
it was said the opposite. אמר רב זריקא אמר רב יהודה. amar
Rav Zerika amar Rav Yehuda. לא שנו אלא שאמרו יתומים אמר לנו
אבא לויתי ופרעתי. lo shanu ela she'amru yetomim amar lanu aba lovisi
ufarati. When is it that the creditor makes an oath to collect
from the heirs? When the heirs are saying our father told us
he paid up. Or they're saying nothing, we don't know. אבל אמרו
אמר לנו אבא, aval amru amar lanu aba, but if they say
that our father told us, לא לויתי, lo lovisi, I never borrowed.
He said our father told us, he has that guy's going around
with a שטר shtar against me, but you should know I never
borrowed that money.
In that case, יפרע שלא בשבועה, yipara shelo bishvua, the creditor can
collect without an oath because basically he's saying you have basically conceded
that you've never paid up the loan. I don't care that you
say you didn't borrow, I got a שטר. shtar. And by you
claiming you didn't borrow, you're conceding you didn't pay up the loan.
שכל אומר לא לויתי כאומר לא פרעתי דמי. shekol omer lo lovisi
k'omer lo parati dami. By saying you didn't borrow, you're saying you
didn't pay. Okay. So this is the idea that somebody or his
heirs that's going to collect from
heirs has to make a שבועה shvua because the guy is not
around to defend himself. So similarly the woman who's coming to collect
from her dead husband's estate has to take an oath that it
hasn't been paid because the husband is not around to defend himself.
And now we get to the last case that the husband is
alive, but he is off in Hawaii. ונפרעת שלא בפניו לא תפרע
אלא בשבועה. v'nifra'at shelo befanav lo tipara ela bishvua. If coming to
collect with the husband not being around, he's in some faraway land,
again you have to make an oath, he's not around to defend
himself.
Yes?
Because, I mean, in the case that this husband died, of course
the husband wouldn't have paid it while he was alive, right? They
didn't get divorced and she's only collecting it so, like, why would
we ever assume that it was paid? The only person who's going
to get it.
So that's a good question because לא ניתנה כתובה לגבות מחיים lo
nitna kesubah ligvos mechayim and logically,
you know, but and if the heirs paid for him, then the
heirs can defend themselves. Yeah, so that's a good question. But the
גמרא Gemara does imagine possibilities like פוגמת כתובתה, pogemes kesubasah, which we
just dealt with, where כתובה kesubah actually can be prepaid, can be
paid off ahead of time. It's rarer, the due date has not
yet come up, but it is possible. Right? You can also, like,
pay off your mortgage at an accelerated rate, although that's different because
the payments have already begun. But it's a good question. But the
reality is there
is yes, it's a good point. You're right. It is unusual and
nevertheless we demand a שבועה. shvua.
You're right.
Is the collection
of כתובה kesubah
always contemporaneous with the giving of a גט? get?
Or with the death of the husband.
But, I mean, at the time he gives her the גט get
and she's...
Oh, no, no. Here's a גט get and now...
exactly, exactly. Why go so far as the case of dying? Like,
if he died, how could he have, you know, when was the
כתובה kesubah paid? Right. Okay, so it could have been prepaid. Okay,
but ah, but now he gave her a גט get and then
he flew off to Hawaii. All right.
When he dies, don't you have to probate the estate or something?
Exactly. Right, exactly.
They pay off כתובה.
kesubah. Right. Are there illustrations where a man's dying and he actually
loves his wife a lot and then he wants to give her
the כתובה kesubah before he dies
so that she doesn't have to deal with the heirs? Right, that's
possible. Right, that's an interesting scenario too. Right. Okay. והביא שליח לפניו
לא שפר לברשות. V'heivi shaliach lefanav lo shepar l'birshus. So now the
husband divorced her, he's off in Hawaii and she has to go
ahead and collect and she needs to make sure of a שבועה
shvua because he's not around to claim whether he did or didn't
pay it. אמר רב אחא שר הבירה. Amar Rav Acha Sar HaBirah.
So רב אחא שר הבירה, Rav Acha Sar HaBirah, interesting name of
him, whatever that means.
Said: Officer of the city?
So who knows. Said: מעשה בא לפני רבי יצחק באנטוכיא,
Maaseh
ba lifnei
Rabbi Yitzchak b'Antochya,
a case came in front of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak in Antioch.
ואמר לו, V'amar lo, and he said the following: לא שנו אלא
כתובת אשה משום חינא. Lo shanu ela kesubas isha mishum china. When
is it that you can collect without the if the
borrower is alive but not present? Right? Maybe an alternative is certainly
you can't just trust the creditor, but you have two possibilities: believe
him with a שבועה shvua or don't have the case until you
can get the guy into the court. So he says, when is
it that we allow the case to go forward with a שבועה?
shvua? That's when you're dealing with a woman collecting her כתובה, Kesubah,
משום חינא, mishum china, because of her, like, you know,
because of like, how to phrase this, but in order that she
should retain
marketability? I guess, anyway,
that it shouldn't hurt her standing in the society, her well-being. Okay,
we're concerned, let's just leave it at that. That we're concerned for
her well-being. Okay? And we don't want her to
be basically, right, we don't want it to be with every, I
mean, that's the whole reason for the כתובה Kesubah is that women
often in society could not provide for themselves and if she can't
collect, she's in a very detrimental situation. So because of our concern
for her standing as a woman in society without this money, without
the ability to collect or whatever, we're going to go ahead and
let her collect as long as she makes a שבועה. shvua.
אבל בעל חוב, Aval baal chov, a normal creditor, that the debtor
is not around, לא, lo, we would not let him make a
שבועה. shvua. We would wait until we could get them both in
court. Okay. ורבא אמר רב נחמן, V'Rava amar Rav Nachman, and רבא
Rava said in the name of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אפילו בעל
חוב, afilu baal chov, even
in
the case of בעל חוב, baal chov, שלא יהא כל אחד ואחד
נוטל מעותיו של חבירו והולך ויושב במדינת הים. shelo yehei kol echad
v'echad notel maosav shel chaveiro v'holech v'yoshev b'mdinas hayam. That what can
happen is people are going to borrow millions of dollars and then
they're going to fly off to Fiji or somewhere that there's no
extradition or whatever and then you'll never be able to collect. So
there has to be some recourse. Maybe בית דין Beis Din uses
its discretion, like okay, maybe if we'll give him six months, you
know, where is he, whatever, but there should certainly be, you know,
an option, if not the default option or whatever, to... and what
would be the problem? והתנא דלת בפני לווין, V'hatana deles bifnei lovin,
not only that, you know, you'll say 'oh, you're so concerned about
the rich creditors.' No, you know, we're concerned about the poor borrowers
because if you have laws in place that are detrimental to the
creditor, don't think you're coming, I mean, this is very important to
appreciate because often we don't, like 'oh, you know, the bad guys
and the good guys' or whatever, you're always in favor of the
rich creditors. No, if the laws don't protect the creditor, then nobody
is lending money to the borrowers, okay? So the borrowers lose out
as well. What? And suspect with the פרוזבול? Pruzbul?
Yeah, that's the thing with the פרוזבול, Pruzbul, although there it's more
about שמיטה, shmitah, but it's the same idea, yes. So yes, we
have to protect the creditors. We don't want people to be able
to loan out money and the people to go and abscond and
go somewhere without being able to pay. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara
ends with that and it would seem very clearly that that's the
הלכה, halacha, right? Down and it's a very persuasive argument. Take a
look at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says: רבא אמר רב נחמן אפילו
בעל חוב, Rava amar Rav Nachman afilu baal chov, ופסק רבינו חננאל
upasak Rabbeinu Chananel דמעשין בכל יום d'maasin b'chol yom שאין נפרעין שלא
בפניו לבעל חוב. she'ein nifrin shelo b'fanav l'baal chov.
That we actually don't collect if the lender isn't around, creditor if
the debtor isn't around, if the debtor isn't around. ולא תחוש להא
דרב נחמן, V'lo sachush l'ha d'Rav Nachman, and we're not concerned of
what רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, even though... ואף על גב דמקשינן
בערכין בפרק שום היתומים ודחינן דחשיס ליה לשובר התם נמי לגבי
הא דרב נחמן לחוש לשובר... v'af al gav d'makshinan b'Erchin b'perek Shum
Hayisomim v'dachinan d'chashish lei l'shover hasam nami l'gavay ha d'Rav Nachman lachush
l'shover... etc. etc. נראה, Nireh, and from that גמרא Gemara it sounds
like דסתמא דש"ס קיימא לן הכי. d'stama d'shas kayma lan hachi. So
not only our גמרא Gemara concludes with that statement, but the סתם
stam of the גמרא Gemara in ערכין Erchin seems like it accepts
רב נחמן's Rav Nachman position that we would collect for a בעל
חוב baal chov if the debtor is not around. If the debtor
isn't around. מכל מקום, Mikol makom, I can see that that's פשט
pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. Nevertheless, כיון דמעשין בכל יום, keivan d'maasin
b'chol yom, in
every day we act in, you know, in against this. Right? Yes,
the גמרא Gemara makes it clear, we collect for the creditor if
the debtor isn't around, but in practice, we never do that. So,
how do we justify that? It's a great תוספות. Tosafos. You see
about like practice against the גמרא. Gemara. סמכו אמאן דדחי ליה בירושלמי.
Samchu amman d'dachi lei b'Yerushalmi. We rely against the בבלי Bavli based
on what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says. דטעמא, D'tama, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks...
says the opposite point. It's
astounding. דכי נפרעין. Dechi nifrin. etcetera, etcetera. And then the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
ends by saying, well let's keep on reading. וכי נמי בירושלמי Ve-chi
nami bi-Yerushalmi then also says in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi דמודו בין אמוראי
דבבל בין אמוראי דארץ ישראל, de-modu bein amora'ei de-Bavel bein amora'ei de-Eretz
Yisrael, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi claims that even the אמוראים Amoraim of בבל
Bavel concede דמשלחים בתרי ג' איגרי, de-meshalechin batrei gimmel igrei,
you send three letters to say, you know, right, summons, three summons.
אי אתי הטיבות, Ei ati hativot, good, he came and we can
deal with it with him. ואי לא, Ve-ei lo, and if not,
then מחלטינן לנכסיה, mechaletinan le-nechasei, then we seize his property. Okay? So
that's like a middle position. That's a reasonable position, right? You summon
him, you give him time or whatever, and if after three summons
he doesn't show, then you go ahead and you execute it without
his presence. But very interesting, right, about the counter, sort of, you
know, competing concerns here and also the practice in defiance of the
פשט pshat of the בבלי. Bavli.
But what he's basically saying is that what we see on the
ground in society, this practice does not prevent creditors from lending money.
Right.
People continue to
lend money, the economy works.
That's a good point too. Maybe also because at least there was
some recourse in terms of the sending of the letters, but you're
right, that's a good point too. מעשה, Ma'aseh, here it's not just
the standard, oh this is the practice we have to justify it,
but the practice shows that the concerns that people won't lend money
were not well-founded for whatever reason. That's an interesting point I hadn't
thought about that. Yeah, Charlie, what do you want to say?
This is a contemporary problem collecting of debts. People hide assets. It's
common in divorce cases.
Sure, of course. Of course. Oh, in divorce cases too, right, yeah.
There's no here, I don't quite follow, but it makes the analogy
that משום חינא mishum china
means that the men will find favor in the eyes of the
woman. The woman wouldn't engage, wouldn't...
That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. תוספות Tosafot reads משום חינא
mishum china easier. תוספות Tosafot reads just משום חינא mishum china is
that we want the woman to still, the men to still find
her attractive and still be concerned, you know, interested in marrying her.
And more generally just means we want to particularly protect her interest
because of her generally disadvantaged position within society. רש"י Rashi makes the
משום חינא mishum china about the men, but תוספות Tosafot says it's
about the women, yeah.
Just systematically, if there's a בבלי Bavli and ירושלמי Yerushalmi things that
disagree with each other, can we go by whichever one or he's
just, you know, picking...
No, no, this was only being used as a defense of because
that's already our practice.
But generally if there's a בבלי Bavli and ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, we go
by the בבלי. Bavli.
Of course. Of course. Yeah. All right, so let's continue. רבי שמעון
אומר כל זמן שתובעת כתובתה. Rabi Shimon omer kol zman she-tova'at ketubatah.
So רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon says this cryptic line,
as long as she's demanding her כתובה, ketubah, then the heirs can
make her swear. But when she's not demanding her כתובה, ketubah, they
can't make her swear. Like, huh? Like, you know, okay, of course
they would only make her swear when she's demanding her כתובה. ketubah.
What are you talking about? So that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
רבי שמעון אהיי? Rabi Shimon a-hei? What part of the משנה Mishnah
is רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon going on and how do we understand
the context? אמר רבי ירמיה אהא, Amar Rabi Yirmiyah a-ha, on this
part. ונפרעת שלא בפניו לא תפרע אלא בשבועה, Ve-nifra'at shelo be-fanav lo
tipara ela bi-shvuah, the statement we made just before this. If he's
not around, she needs a שבועה. shvuah. לא שנא למזוני ולא שנא
לכתובה. Lo shanya le-mezonei ve-lo shanya le-ketubah.
Now that would include two cases. One is he's not around and
they're still married, but
she needs to put food on the table and he has to
pay regular food bills. So she needs to sell off from the
estate to pay for the food bills when he's off in Hawaii.
Okay, so that's one case of, and she has to make a
שבועה, shvuah, he did not deposit money in my account before he
left for the food and therefore I should be able to take
some of his property and sell it for the food. That's one
case. And the other case is he divorced me and went to
Hawaii and he never paid me the כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so that's
two implicit scenarios in שלא בפניו. shelo be-fanav.
Is that really the property that she's got title to that he's
eating the פירות peirot from in the marriage? It's really her own
stuff she's selling.
No, it could be his totally his stuff. Okay. ולא שנא למזוני
ולא שנא לכתובה. Ve-lo shanya le-mezonei ve-lo shanya le-ketubah. ואתא רבי שמעון
למימר כל זמן שתובעת כתובתה יורשין משביעין אותה. Ve-ata Rabi Shimon le-meimar
kol zman she-tova'at ketubatah yorshin mashbi'in otah. And רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon
says, look, there's a difference between מזונות mezonot and כתובה. ketubah. If
she's asking for כתובה ketubah payment, then they're divorced, then she can
be made to take an oath that the כתובה ketubah has not
already been paid up. But אינה תובעת כתובתה, einah tova'at ketubatah, if
they're married and she's not asking for כתובה ketubah payment, she's just
asking for the food bills to be paid, in that case אין
יורשין משביעין אותה. ein yorshin mashbi'in otah. It's a funny use of
the phrase יורשים yorshim which the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
But okay, anyways the husband's estate cannot, or the בית דין Beit
Din won't make her take an oath because again, the woman needs
to put food on the table, we're not going to make her
go through this process, it's a certain urgency, it's an ongoing responsibility,
we're not going to make her take an oath that she has
not had that money already used up, you know, the husband hasn't
already deposited that money in her account.
Use of the word יורשים, yorshim, they use the word... well, but
right, because they use it earlier.
All right, but the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge us, so
let's take a look. וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דתנן, Ve-kamiflgi bi-plugta de-tenan, and
they are debating the following debate, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah.
ובני כהנים גדולים. U-vnei Kohanim Gedolim. דחנן, De-Chanan, excuse me, ובני כהנים...
u-vnei Kohanim... בני כהנים גדולים. Bnei Kohanim Gdolim. Okay. דתנן, D'tnan, we
taught in a משנה. Mishnah. מי שהלך למדינת הים, Mi shehalach l'medinas
hayam, guy went to Hawaii, ואשתו תבעת מזונות, v'ishto tva'as mezonos, and
his wife says, "I need to put food on the table." They're
married. חנן אומר, Chanan omer, תשבע בסוף ולא תשבע בתחילה. tishava basof
v'lo tishava bitchila.
If there's a concern that she's been pre- that she's already been
given money for it, you can't make her take that oath now.
You know when you could take make her take an oath? When
the guy dies, or when the guy divorces her, and then she
comes to collect the כתובה, kesubah, then you can say, "Take an
oath that I never- that all that money that you used to
pay for, you know, the מזונות mezonos when I was off in
Hawaii or my father was off in Hawaii, that that was not
money that had already been prepaid to you." So you can make
her take oaths about any money that she might have already been
prepaid when she's coming to collect the כתובה, kesubah, but not right
now when she's just coming to put food on the table. Okay.
So that's at the end, but not at the beginning. נחלקו עליו
בני כהנים גדולים. Nechleku alav Bnei Kohanim Gdolim.
The children of the כהנים גדולים, Kohanim Gdolim, funny group of people.
I don't- I don't know. ואמרו, V'amru, תשבע בתחילה ובסוף. tishava bitchila
u'vasof.
Okay. Let her- she- nope, if she- when she comes to collect
her כתובה kesubah she has to swear she hasn't been paid the
כתובה, kesubah, and when she's coming to collect מזונות mezonos and when
they're still married and he's somewhere else, she has to swear that
she hasn't been prepaid money for the מזונות. mezonos. So that seems
like this debate. Okay. רבי שמעון כחנן. Rebbi Shimon k'Chanan. Rebbi Shimon
is like Chanan; he says only when she's coming to collect the
כתובה kesubah will there be an oath, not when she's coming to
collect מזונות. mezonos. ורבנן כבני כהנים גדולים. V'Rabanan k'Vnei Kohanim Gdolim.
And the Rabbis that he's arguing and says, "Nope, she has to
take an oath whenever she's collecting שלא בפניו." shelo bifanav. That would
be this opposite position. Okay. So,
the גמרא Gemara says, so that seems like a very reasonable read.
מתקיף לה רב ששת. Masif lah Rav Sheshes. Rav Sheshes says, "I
just got one problem with that read." האי, Hai, יורשין משביעין אותה.
Yorshin mashbi'in osah. It shouldn't say the heirs can make her take
the oath since we said the issue was whether that he's off
in מדינת הים. medinas hayam. It should say בית דין משביעין אותה
מיבעי ליה. Beis Din mashbi'in osah mibaya lei. There's no יורשים yorshim
here, right? It's- you're saying the context is he's off in מדינת
הים. medinas hayam. So whether it's about the כתובה kesubah or about
the מזונות, mezonos, there's no heirs in either case. He's alive, he's
just off in מדינת הים. medinas hayam. So that was a very
nice explanation, but the word "heirs" doesn't fit. Okay, so let's try
again. אלא אמר רב ששת. Ela amar Rav Sheshes. Aha! So what
Reb Shimon is going on the following statement in the משנה. Mishnah.
הלכה מקבר בעלה לבית אביה. Halcha mikever ba'alah l'veis aviha.
The whole case of the אפוטרופיא. apotropya. Sorry,
that would be their debate, but that's not what's going on here.
הלכה מקבר בעלה לבית אביה או שחזרה לבית חמיה. Halcha mikever ba'alah
l'veis aviha o shechazrah l'veis chameiha. Okay, so the husband died and
she went back to her father's house or she went back to
her father-in-law's house. ולא נעשית אפוטרופיא, V'lo na'asis apotropya, and she did
not continue to be the manager of the estate. אין היורשין משביעין
אותה, Ein hayorshin mashbi'in osah, the heirs cannot make her take an
oath because the husband had exempted her from oaths from the past
events. ואם נעשית אפוטרופיא, V'im na'asis apotropya, and if she became a
manager, יורשין משביעין אותה על העתיד לבוא ואין משביעין אותה על מה
שעבר.
yorshin mashbi'in osah al he'asid lavo v'ein mashbi'in osah
al mah she'avar. Okay, they can make her take an oath on
future dealings, right? We everybody remembers that. ואתא רבי שמעון למימר. V'asa
Rebbi Shimon l'meimar. Now Reb Shimon is saying, no, כל זמן שתובעת
כתובתה יורשין משביעין אותה. kol zman shetova'as kesubasah yorshin mashbi'in osah. If
she actually- she- the heirs cannot make her take an oath on
her dealings as the אפוטרופיא. apotropya. They- you know- out- on her
dealings as the manager of the estate. Even on new events. Okay.
When she comes to collect her כתובה, kesubah, if they have any
concerns of how she managed the estate as the אפוטרופיא, apotropya, you'll
make her take that oath when she comes to collect her כתובה.
kesubah. But she cannot be demanded to take that oath in her
role as an אפוטרופוס. apotropos. Okay. כל זמן שתובעת כתובתה יורשין משביעין
אותה.
Kol
zman
shetova'as kesubasah yorshin mashbi'in osah. אינה תובעת כתובתה, Einah tova'as kesubasah,
just in her role of an אפוטרופוס, apotropos, אין היורשין משביעין אותה.
ein hayorshin mashbi'in osah. They cannot. Now why not? Here they are,
here she is, she's managing their estate. Why can't they make her
take an oath? וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דאבא שאול ורבנן. V'kamifligi b'plugta d'Abba Shaul
v'Rabanan.
It's the debate of Abba Shaul and the Rabbis. דתנן, D'tnan, we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, אפוטרופוס שמינו אבי יתומים, apotropos sheminu avi
yesomim, an אפוטרופוס apotropos that was appointed by the father for the
heirs before he died. And we're going to assume that that's the
case, even though it never says that was the case in the
משנה, Mishnah, we're going to assume that he appointed his wife the
אפוטרופוס, apotropos, the executor of the estate before he died. Okay. And
the heirs are all underage, so they need somebody to manage their
affairs. So they're not in a position to appoint her or not.
Got it? They're all underage, they need somebody to be appointed, and
that- and the father appointed his wife before he died. Okay. So
what's the הלכה? halacha? Can they make her take an oath? Can
they make this person when, you know, take an oath that he's
handling- he or she is handling the estate properly? Okay. So, אפוטרופוס
שמינו אבי יתומים ישבע. apotropos sheminu avi yesomim yishava. He will have
to take an oath because any executor, any manager of an estate
can be- you can demand that they take an oath that they've
handled the estate properly. Like the storekeeper, you can demand, you know,
that somebody you made the storekeeper, you can demand that your wife
take an oath. Any executor you can demand they take an oath.
That's a general rule. So even if it was appointed by- By
the father, מינוי בית דין minuy Beis Din appointed by the court,
לא ישבע lo yishava cannot. Now, what's the logic? The logic is
that if somebody's appointed by the father because he obviously has a
relationship with the father, he'll accept that responsibility even if he knows
he might have to make an oath. Whereas if the court asks
somebody, okay, that's gonna be the opposite argument. The court actually asks
somebody to be an executor, it's like why should I take on
that responsibility, especially if they're gonna make me take an oath? Like
no, I refuse to be an executor. So therefore in order to
get people to accept an appointment of the court, we have to
exempt them from an oath. מינוי בית דין minuy Beis Din לא
ישבע. lo yishava. אבא שאול Abba Shaul אומר חילוף הדברים, omer chiluf
hadvarim, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says exact opposite. מינוי בית דין ישבע,
minuy Beis Din yishava, if the court appoints him take an oath
because if the court appoints you that's a oh look, the court
trusts me, it makes me executors of people's estates, so you're willing
to do the oath because you have the recognition of the court.
מינוי אבי יתומים, minuy avi yesomim, if it's just some debt I
owe to the dead father, לא ישבע, lo yishava, I if I
you can't make me take an oath, you make me take an
oath I'll refuse to be the executor. Okay, so here's the debate
about which type of an אפיטרופוס apotropos would we exempt in order
to encourage people to take on that role. Alright, so that's the
debate. How does that map on? So we're assuming the case is
that the husband made his wife the executor before he died. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon כאבא שאול, k'Abba Shaul, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
like אבא שאול Abba Shaul that the heirs can make her take
an oath when she comes to collect the כתובה, kesuvah, but not
take an oath as her role of executor, because he was appointed
by the father. And if you're appointed by the father, you don't
have to take an oath. ורבנן כרבנן, v'Rabbanan k'Rabbanan, and the Rabbis
like the Rabbis who argue on אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. They say
no, even if you're appointed by the father, whoever's appointed by the
father has to take an oath. Okay, so this is the question.
Our משנה mishna said that the woman who's an אפיטרופוס apotropos over
the heirs' money, okay, has to take an oath. So the גמרא
gemara is saying let's assume the scenario is that the father appointed
her. Okay, and then it's saying that even appointed by the father,
the heirs can make her take an oath. And and then רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying no, they can't make her take an
oath, they can make her take an oath to collect the כתובה,
kesuvah, but they can't make her take an oath in her role
as אפיטרופוס. apotropos. Okay, that's another good read. So let's see why
the גמרא gemara doesn't like that one. מתקיף לה אביי, maskif lah
Abaye, so אביי Abaye challenged that. האי כל זמן שדורשת כתובתה, hai
kol zman she'doreshes kesuvatah, the language of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
as long as she's collecting her כתובה, kesuvah, they can make her
take an oath. אם דורשת מיבעי ליה, im doreshes mibaye leh,
since רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is coming to limit when she can
take an oath, he should have said no, she doesn't take an
oath as an אפיטרופוס, apotropos, only if she demands her כתובה. kesuvah.
כל זמן kol zman means that he's coming to actually increase the
ability to make her take an oath, not limit the ability to
take an oath. Okay, אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, so the
third read. אהא, aha, כתב לה נדר ושבועה אין לי עלייך, kasav
lah neder ushvuah ein li alaich, he's going earlier and earlier back
in our משנה mishna to figure the context of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Now we're going like three משניות mishnayos back to say what
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is referring to. Okay, כתב לה נדר ושבועה
אין לי עלייך, kasav lah neder ushvuah ein li alaich, I don't
have any שבועה shvuah on you. איני יכול להשביע, eini yachol lehashvia,
he can't make her take an oath. נדר ושבועה אין לי ולא
ליורשיי ולא לבאים ברשותי עלייך ולא ליורשייך ולא לבאים ברשותי, neder ushvuah
ein li velo leyorshai velo leba'im birshuti alaich velo leyorshaich velo leba'im
birshuti,
so any of my heirs, any of yours, אינן יכולין להשביע לא
הוא ולא יורשיו ולא הבאים ברשותו לא היא ולא יורשיה ולא הבאים
ברשותה. einan yecholin lehashvia lo hu velo yorshav velo haba'im birshuto lo
hi velo yorsheha velo haba'im birshusah. Remember that whole משנה? mishna? Fine.
Okay, so the way that it's waived. ואתא רבי שמעון למימר, ve'asa
Rabbi Shimon lemeimar, now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon comes along and says:
כל זמן שדורשת כתובתה, kol zman she'doreshes kesuvatah,
you know what? Even if it's waived, it doesn't matter. As long
as whenever she demands her כתובה, kesuvah, יורשין משביעין אותה, yorshin mashbi'in
osah, they can still make her take an oath. How can they
make her take an oath? He waived it. Here's how.
וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דאבא שאול בן אימא מרים ורבנן. vekamifligi b'plugta d'Abba Shaul
ben Imma Miriam v'Rabbanan. Remember אבא שאול בן אימא מרים? Abba Shaul
ben Imma Miriam? אבא שאול בן אימא מרים Abba Shaul ben Imma
Miriam said in principle she's exempt, but in practice she has to
take an oath. Why? Because אמרו חכמים הבא ליפרע מנכסי יתומים לא
יפרע אלא בשבועה. amru chachamim haba lipara minichsei yesomim lo yipara ela
bishvuah.
So he can waive any oaths that are his to waive, that
are things that would have been an oath to him. But when
she actually comes to collect her כתובה kesuvah and she's coming to
be פורע מנכסי יתומים, porea minichsei yesomim,
that she always has to make a שבועה, shvuah, that he can't
waive. Remember that אבא שאול בן אימא מרים? Abba Shaul ben Imma
Miriam? So what רבי... Rabbi... we're no longer אפיטרופוס. apotropos.
So what
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying is, you say if it's waived
it's waived and she should be totally free from a שבועה. shvuah.
I
say כל זמן שדורשת כתובתה, kol zman she'doreshes kesuvatah, whenever she's coming
to collect her כתובה, kesuvah, I don't care what you waived, she
has to make a שבועה. shvuah.
Wait, even if he's alive and they're getting...
no, no, no, no, no. He died because it's being פורע מנכסי
יתומים. porea minichsei yesomim. Okay, right. So now we're very close. Okay,
we got it. Good. Totally waived and he says I don't care,
whenever you're collecting from יתומים, yesomim, you need a שבועה. shvuah. So
there's only one last question.
מתקיף לה רב פפא, maskif lah Rav Papa, רב פפא Rav Papa
asked: התינח כל זמן... hatenach kol zman... That explains the first phrase
of the of of Rabbi Shimon's statement. As long as she's demanding
her כתובה, kesubah, even if it's been waived, she always has to
take an oath. אינה תובעת כתובתה מאי איכא למימר? Eina tovass kesubasah
mai ika lemeymar? What about the second half of Rabbi Shimon's statement?
He says, and when she's not demanding her כתובה, kesubah, she doesn't
have to take an oath. Okay, of course not. Why did you
need to say that? Everybody agrees to that. He waived it all.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב פפא, Ella amar Rav
Pappa, here's how we explain the last piece. I agree with you
the first phrase. The first phrase he's saying waiving doesn't help when
she's coming to collect her כתובה. kesubah. And the last phrase is
saying לאפוקי מדרבי אליעזר מחלוקתו. L'afukei mi'd'Rabbi Eliezer machlokto. Remember the whole
issue with רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that
the that basically the question is that's the other part of the
משנה mishna where the question is, can a husband make his wife
swear if she's running the shop? Or can he make her swear
about the dough or whatever? And basically there, it was according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, he can even make his wife swear about
the use of the dough. According to the חכמים Chachamim though, not
that, but if she's running the shop, he can make her swear.
Comes along רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
very מחמיר machmir in one case and very מקיל meykil in the
other. He's very מחמיר machmir to say, I don't care how much
was waived, whenever she's collecting her כתובה, kesubah, שבועה. shvuah. On the
other hand, if nothing and on the other hand, if it's not
about the כתובה, kesubah, if it's during the marriage itself, I don't
care whether she's running the business, you cannot make her make a
שבועה shvuah when it's not about the כתובה. kesubah. So about the
כתובה kesubah he always demands it, about everything else he never does.
One last final interesting point, again, practically, take a quick look at
תוספות לאפוקי. Tosfos L'afukei. I know we're over time, but I just
have to read this to you about ten lines down in לאפוקי,
L'afukei, end of the line which says the words ולפני רבנו תם.
u'lifnei Rabbeinu Tam. You see the line that says the words לפני
רבנו תם? lifnei Rabbeinu Tam?
Yeah,
באישה שהושיבה בעלה חנונית b'isha she'hoshiba ba'ala chanunis ומינה אפוטרופיא, u'minah apitropya,
right? Which is very Ashkenaz women were really business women, okay? And
she was running the whole business, והייתה נושאת ונותנת הרבה מעות בבית,
v'hayisa noses v'nosenes harbei ma'os babayis, and she was completely calling control
all the accounts. ואומרת לבעלה שאינם שלו, v'omeres l'ba'ala she'einam shelo, okay?
And she basically told her husband like, you know, that they weren't
his, I don't know, they belonged to other people,
whatever the case was, there was some question. Or maybe the husband
suspected that she had pocketed the money, whatever the issue was. The
husband suspected her of something and wanted to make her take an
oath. לא השביעה בחיי בעלה. Lo hisbi'ah b'chayei ba'ala. And רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam refused to let the husband make her take a you
know force let the husband make her take an oath. Why? דכיון
דאוקמינן כזמן שתובעת כרבי שמעון כאבא שאול בן אימי, D'keivan d'okminan k'zman
she'tova'as k'Rabbi Shimon k'Abba Shaul ben Immi, blah blah blah, since basically
the גמרא Gemara ends like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we פסק pasken
and we פסק pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon like אבא שאול
בן אימי, Abba Shaul ben Immi, we פסק pasken the other half
of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, I know, but you'll read תוספות.
Tosfos. He explains why we פסק pasken half of רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, we פסק pasken אבא שאול בן אימי, Abba Shaul ben Immi,
we פסק pasken the other half of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So
this is quite fascinating, right? Which is important to know that I
mean and it I think it also somewhat reflects the reality of
women of women's empowerment and women as businesswomen in אשכנז Ashkenaz that
basically, you know, רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam פסק paskened that even if
the husband has his wife running the whole business, against the against
the סתם משנה stam mishna before, you know, sort of through this
back door here that we opened up with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
says the husband can't make his wife take any oath if she's
running the business. The only oaths are when she comes to collect
the כתובה. kesubah.
Very
interesting end to that סוגיא. sugya. Okay.
What? These orphans, doesn't it make a difference if they're minors and
all that? You'd have to think as legally as you did last
night.